<?xml version='1.0' ?><!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
	<title>Concepts</title>
	<chapter id="conceptIntroduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>A service oriented architecture is build from functionality
			captured in services. Hence, what services exist in SOA is the most
			interesting question for a analyst, software architect or developer.
			Service repositories are the most important tool to answer questions
			like:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>What services are available?</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>What is the contract of a service?</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>In what state is the service? Can I use it for production?
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>What dependencies does it have?</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>...</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Usually a service repository will import WSDLs, XSDs and other
			documents to describe the available services. However, WSDL is a
			rather technical webservice related description of a service. It does
			not define the complete formal service contract independent of the
			technology being used. E.g. the version of a service and it’s
			dependencies are not defined or considered meaningful to a certain
			technology stack.</para>
		<para>Another issue is, that often SOA Governance will define
			additional rules that apply to service contract. The Governance board
			has to review every service contract, whether it meets the compliance rules, it has
			defined. This is going to reduce the agility in service development.
		</para>
		<para>Xtext Service Repository resolves these issues in two
			ways:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Use DSLs to describe formal service contracts with all required
					details</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Use model validators to verify formal constraints without the
					need to involve the SOA governance board</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Use code generation to apply technical rules implicitly, e.g.
					all webservices use document/literal-wrapped SOAP style and schema
					centralization</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</chapter>
	<chapter id="ServiceModelingConcepts">
		<title>Service modeling concepts</title>
		<section id="Datamodel">
			<title>The data model</title>
			<para>The data model in a SOA approach may be separated into two
				major parts:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Canonical data model</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Non canonical data model</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>

			<section id="CanonicalDataModel">
				<title>Canonical data model</title>
				<para>
					The canonical data model defines data types that are
					standardized to
					some extent. It is the &quot;common language&quot; Whenever data
					are exchanged between different systems, the canonical data model
					should be used as it protects the user from frequent changes. A
					canonical data model is scoped to a domain or subdomain. Namespace
					that belong to the canonical data model are called
					<emphasis role="bold">domain namespace</emphasis>
					s.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section id="NonCanonicalDataModel">
				<title>Non canonical data model</title>
				<para>
					The non canonical data model defines data types that are
					<emphasis>not</emphasis>
					standardized. The canonical data model is the &quot;local
					language&quot; of an application or system. Hence, it is considered
					internal and should only be used internally by that system or
					application. The non canonical data model enables frequent changes
					to the data model in a &quot;safe&quot; area, that does not affect
					other systems or applications. Namespaces that belong to the non
					canonical data model are called
					<emphasis role="bold">internal namespace</emphasis>
					s
				</para>
			</section>
			<section id="DomainsAndNamespaces">
				<title>Domains and namespaces</title>
				<para>The canonical and the non canonical datamodel are organized into domains which 
				are reflected by namespaces. For each subdomain there exists a respective domain-namespace.
				Domains and there subdomains are defined in the business model. Hence, domain namespaces 
				contain the respective subdomain of the canonical datamodel and their related public services.
				</para>
				<para>
				Domain namespaces are complemented by internal namespaces that contain the non canonical datamodel
				and private services. Whatever is defined in an internal namespace should only be internally as 
				the name suggests. Internal namespaces contain fragile API.
				</para>
				<example>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject role="html">
							<imagedata align="center" fileref="images/namespaces.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</example>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="EncapsulationOfServices">
			<title>Encapsulation of services</title>
			<para>Often, a SOA will be built from already existing systems and
				interfaces. However, the services already available will usually not
				suit very well with the larger scope of an enterprise wide IT
				architecture as they have been developed with specific usage
				scenarios in mind.</para>
			<para>
				A good approach to provide more suitable services, would be to define
				new standard service contracts which hide the technical details of the
				service implementation provided by a certain system. The new service
				contract would be
				<emphasis role="bold">public</emphasis>
				service, while the already available technical service
				implementation will be considered
				<emphasis role="bold">private</emphasis>
				. This will shield consumers of the public service from rather
				frequent changes of the technical service implementations as well as
				their interfaces.
				
				<example>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject role="html">
							<imagedata align="center" fileref="images/PublicEncapsPrivateService.png" scalefit="true"/>
						</imageobject>
						<caption>A public service encapsulating a private service</caption>
					</mediaobject>
				</example>

			</para>
		</section>


		<section id = "ModelPerspectives">
			<title>Perspectives in a SOA model</title>
			In a SOA model you can take different perspectives, depending on the
			matter of interest.

			<section id = "BusinessModelPerspective">
				<title>Business view</title>
				<para>The business view gives a perspective on what makes up the
					business
					of a company. It is typically organized in
					domains which may
					be reflected by the company's organizational
					structure. The business
					model also defines business functions that are
					supported by the organization or certain organizational roles.
					to build solutions from business functions.
				</para>
				<para>Business capabilities are used to define what can be done in the
					business sense. They can be compared to use cases, yet they do not
					define actors as they are designed for reuse 
					A business capability might be e.g. &quot;Lookup a customer by her
					address&quot;.
					Business capabilities relate to services or service operations
					defined in the service model.</para>
			</section>

			<section id="SolutionPerspective">
				<title>Solutions</title>
				<para>Solutions support the business of company. Solutions are
					available as applications or bundles of application that solve a
					certain problem, e.g. a customer self care solution. In SOA
					solutions will reuse business function by using services that
					support those business functions. Solutions are the end consumers
					of services.</para>
				<example>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject role="html">
							<imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Solutions.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</example>
			</section>

			<section id="ServiceModelPerspective">
				<title>Service model</title>
				<para>The service model let's you look at service contracts
					and data types. The service model defines domain and internal namespaces, 
					which in turn define business objects, enumerations, services and exception
					types. </para>
				<section>
					<title>Versions and lifecycle states</title>
					<para>Different consumers	of a service may require a different version of the service. Hence, several different
						versions of a service and related business objects etc. may be deployed in the same 
						runtime environment. Generally the latest compatible version will be used when a dependcy
						to another service or business object is being declared. Whether a newer version is 
						compatible to it's previous version or not is inferred from the version number increment.
						If the major version.</para> 
					<para>Business objects, enumerations and services are versioned by having a version number. 
						Versionnumber may be qualified with major and minor version numbers and so seperated by dots. 
						A namespace may declare several different versions of a service etc. Dependencies to other 
						services and types are qualified by the name and a version constraint, that selects the latest 
						applicable version.</para>
					<para> Whether a certain version matches the version constraint depends also on 
						the lifecycle states of the dependency owner and the target object of the 
						dependency. 
						<example>There may be a service <classname>CustomerEntityService</classname> in version <code>1.2</code> 
							which has a service operation <methodname>getCustomer</methodname> that returns a list
							of <classname>Customer</classname>s in the latest minor version of major version <code>1</code>.
							Be <classname>Customer</classname> available in version <code>1.0</code> in the lifecycle state <code>productive</code>
							, meaning it is ready for production use and let's say we have a <classname>Customer</classname> in 
							version <code>1.1</code> that is in state <code>development</code> meaning it is ready for development 
							purposes. In a production environment the latter version would not yet be available. Hence, in the production
							environment the dependency to <classname>Customer</classname> in major version 1 would actually resolve to 
							<classname>Customer</classname> version <code>1.0</code>, while in the the development environment it
							would resolve to version <code>1.1</code>.
						</example>
					</para>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Services</title>
					<para>
						A public service usually relates to a business
						function in	the business model. A service provides functional capabilities
						implemented	as service operations.</para>
				</section>
				
				<section>
					<title>Business Objects</title>
					<para>Business objects are complex types with one ore more attributes. Attibutes have a name, 
						a type with a version constraint if it is a business object or enumeration, an 
						optional many cardinality and some other optional flags.</para>
				</section>
				
				<section>
					<title>Enumerations</title>
					<para>Enumerations declare all possible values that an attribute or parameter of
						that type may have.</para>
				</section>
				
				<section>
					<title>Exceptions</title>
					<para>As in many programming languages, exceptions describe an unexpected 
						behaviour or erro condition.</para>
				</section>

			</section>
			<section id="ModulePerspective">
				<title>Modules</title>
				<para>Modules assemble services into modules. The module has a unique version number.</para>
			</section>
			
			<section id="EnvironmentPerspective">
				<title>Runtime environment</title>
				<para>The environment defines, what makes up the IT infrastructure
					that hosts services and solutions. Typical parts of an environment
					are hosts, application servers, databases and so on. Typically a
					company has a production, test and a development environment.</para>
			</section>
			
			<section id="BindingPerspective">
				<title>Service binding</title>
				<para>The binding perspective wires services to an environment, where they are 
					supposed to be hosted together. It defines protocols, servers hosting the services 
					(and implicitly their endpoints) as well as assigned SLAs and policies like 
					security policies.</para>
				<mediaobject >
					<imageobject role="html">
						<imagedata align="center" fileref="images/CoreDSLs.png" scale="100"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
					
				<para>
					Every binding declares what it binds from the service model to which environment. 
					Bindings can be declared on several levels with regard to the service model:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><classname>ModuleBinding</classname> refers to a module to be bound to a given
							environment. Hence, the services provided by the referenced module will be bound to the 
							given environment using the defined default protocols defined for the whole module in
							the ModuleBinding definition. Alternatively the defaults can be overridden defining 
							<classname>ServiceBindings</classname> 
						</listitem>
						<listitem><classname>DomainBinding</classname> references a namespace 
							(domain namespace or internal namespace) from service model. DomainBindings 
							are always toplevel binding in the binding model and have name to be referable
						</listitem>
						<listitem><classname>ServiceBinding</classname> refers to a specific service 
							by name and a version constraint. <classname>ServiceBindings</classname> override 
							the definitions of the surrounding <classname>DomainBinding</classname>
						</listitem>
						<listitem><classname>OperationBinding</classname>s refer to a specific service 
							operation with the fullqualified name of the operation and version constraint 
							selecting the owning service. Definitions from a surrounding 
							<classname>ServiceBinding</classname> will overridden.
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>The perspective supports convention over configuration
					in that one would define a default binding configuration for a certain namespace. 
					The defaults may the be overridden for a specific service or even a 
					specific operation of a service.</para>
			</section>
			
			<section id="SLAPerspective">
				<title>Service level agreements</title>
				<para>Service Level Agreement can be declared in a SLA model. Service Level Agreement declare
					properties properties like service availability, maximum downtimes, responsible service owners
					and so on. SLAs are generally scoped to an environment. Hence, SLAs must be assigned to a 
					namespace or service in the binding model. As each binding is scoped to an environment, assigned
					SLAs are implicitly scoped to the environment for which the respective binding has
					been declared</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section id="ModelingWithDSLs">
			<title>Modeling with Domain Specific Langugaes</title>
			<para>Domain Specific Languages (short DSLs) are textual or graphical languages designed for specific 
			problem domain. Xtext Service Repostiory describes the central assets of a SOA as explained in the 
			section <xref linkend="ModelPerspectives"/> using a specific textual DSL for each perspective. The 
			Xtext Service Repository DSL editors will support with code completion.</para>
			<para> As services
			are the most important assets of a SOA, the Service DSL is the most important one. Create a new 
			Service DSL file to define namespace, business objects and services. To define a runtime environment 
			you are going to create an Environment DSL file. To finally declare, where the defines services run bind 
			them with DomainBinding, ServiceBinding or even OperationBinding to the environment or more specific, 
			certain servers in the target environment. Create a new Binding DSL file to declare such a binding.</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
</book>